Oh Vasudeva Sutent even come such are no
Ramadan 'im Devaki param anand krishna
monday before we start a quick
announcement next week there won't be
any classes the Tuesday Wednesday and
Friday classes are cancelled
there's the world Parliament of
Religions which is going on in Toronto
now so I'm going that day after tomorrow
so Tuesday class Wednesday class and
Friday classes are cancelled but of
course they are to tomorrow the morning
program is there I'm here giving the
talk so especially the next week's
Friday gita class it won't be there next
week but the week after that of course
did with a classically we were studying
the Bhagavad Gita second chapter where
Shri Krishna is teaching about the real
nature of the self and we studied the
sixteenth verse of the second chapter I
mentioned that it's a difficult verse a
very profound verse let's chant it again
and then we will proceed sixteenth verse
na citavi deity ba na sir Toby dirty
Bravo
Nawab Ovid dirty
[Music]
Europa - tanta uber rapid reach 20 -
Anna you start or - if he thought were -
if he found verse which says that the
the unreal defaults never really existed
and the real they are the real self the
Atman what we truly are it can never not
exist so what he's basically saying is
the entire world of experience all those
things which are created and destroyed
for us they appear to exist for some
time this world our bodies our people we
know that appear to exist for some time
but that's an appearance that's what has
been pointed out and do you remember the
underlying logic of this approach that a
distinction was made between an
intrinsic property and an accidental or
incidental property and you remember the
example that I used about the potato
being boiled and its heart and the water
boils and the water is hot and the pan
in which with the water's boiling that's
hot but none of these things are hot in
themselves they gain heat and then they
lose heat whereas the fire underneath is
always hot as long as it's burning it's
always hot so the pan and the water and
the potato they all borrow heat as it
were from the fire why is it wet they
actually do borrow heat from the fire
and they lose heat also so the heat is
an extrinsic or an accidental property
for these the pan and the water and the
and the potato and notice the nature of
an accidental property or an incidental
property it comes and goes I gave the
example of borrowed money buying things
on on credit so it comes and goes
it's borrowed it
doesn't belong to to that entity which
means the lesson we take away the
principle we take away from it is that
accidental or incidental properties are
those which are not intrinsic to the
very nature of a thing they come and go
a thing can be with it and can be
without it also and can can possess it
for a time being so what if this is
understood now applied to existence
itself applying it to existence what
will happen if if existence is an
incidental property sounds very
philosophical or abstract but it's not
remember incidental properties are
gained and lost if existence is an
incidental property it will be gained
and lost what is the meaning of gaining
existence of losing existence
it simply means being created and
destroyed being born and dying coming
into being and going and losing
existence coming into existence and
losing existence in other words what you
call a thing which is created and
destroyed born and dies impermanent in
sanskrit an idea impermanent so what did
we derive from this those things which
are impermanent do not have existence as
their in the intrinsic nature as their
very nature they borrow existence now
two interesting things come out of this
that there is space here also I think
you can sit here and I think there's
space here right okay two things come
out of this one is what do they borrow
existence from are you with me so far I
always this is a difficult subject if
you get the hang of it it's not
difficult I give the example of you know
then the Tintin comics we used to read
read as kids there is love
of calculus those yeah I can see some
people nodding you read it the professor
calculus is explaining some complicated
nuclear reaction to Tintin and Captain
Haddock and Thompson and Thomson the
lives they're walking along and at at
one and you can see Captain Haddock
scowling because he can't understand
what's going on and and professor
calculus looks back and says do you
follow me
and the captain's couch and says yes I'm
right behind you so not follow me in
that sense what does it mean to gain
existence and lose exists what does it
mean in that case two things it means
one is that these things are not
intrinsic existence is not intrinsic to
in the impermanent entities which by
which we mean everything in this world
is impermanent everything in this world
is impermanent and that means they have
borrowed existence one the second thing
is it means it has borrowed existence
from something that must be something
which has lent existence which has
existence as an intrinsic property which
really what would it mean to have
existence as an intrinsic property
remember fire has Heat as an intrinsic
property which means as long as fire is
burning there is heat if something has
existence as an intrinsic property if it
has an incidental property it will be
born it will die it will be created and
destroyed if it has existence as an
intrinsic property what will happen to
that thing do you remember it'll always
exist fire has heat as an intrinsic
property it's always hot if something
has existence as an intrinsic property
it will always exist by that logic now
you might say that all this is fine but
in the real world but interesting the
use of the word term or the term real
real literally means existing in the
existing world where is such a thing
something which has intrinsic existence
which exists forever which is not born
and destroyed
do you remember Shankar Acharya pointed
out we needed a close reading of the
shaft Shankar's commentary on the verse
he pointed out son had a son but a son
has the the pot exist a pot is the house
is the elephant is house pot elephant
are different they're different from
each other they are not the same thing
but in each of them we have the
intuition of existence is is they don't
pay any attention to it
he said if you remember our experience
has this dual nature all our experience
everything in our life has this dual
nature right now for example you're
experiencing that I I am here and this
is a room and here is a chapel here is a
Swami there is speech going on that
there's some sound going on I am
thinking listening but these are all
experiences you are having now but
Shankar Acharya pointed out each of
these experiences has a dual nature one
part is the thing which you are
experiencing the other part is the
existence of that thing notice I am look
at the word M it means existence the
room is the chapel is speech is how do
you experience speech do you experience
it as existing or non-existing you
obviously do not experience anything is
non existing because if it was non
existing you wouldn't experience it so
literally the experience everything the
experience is pervaded by isness a sense
of being and Shankar Acharya takes pains
to point out it is very well established
in your experience you're actually
experiencing it existence and it's an
interesting thing if you're experiencing
if you experience a book there is a book
and you are experiencing it if you're
experiencing existence
there must be something called existence
let me repeat that if you're
experiencing a book there must be
something called a book which you have
in your experience if you're
experiencing existence
there must be something called existence
which you are experiencing so there is
this one underlying business
which way'd anta calls pure being such
pure being existence literally suck
means pure being isness which is always
available to us which never goes out of
existence and do you remember we had all
those interesting questions if a part is
destroyed so the part is not and
Shankaracharya would say first of all
the broken part is the easiness
continues in the broken part and there
are other parts so he suppose all parts
are destroyed well there are there is
the clock and there's the house and then
there was a very interesting question
suppose everything in the universe is
destroyed where will existence be and
then very interesting conclusion was all
these things in the universe all names
and forms they manifest existence if the
names and forms are gone existence
remains but there's no way of
appreciating it all these things we
discussed so the conclusion was in this
world of experience whatever we are
experiencing in the world there is an
easiness which is permanent which is not
born which does not die that never goes
out of existence it cannot logically and
there is this continuous stream of
appearances things and places and people
and events our own bodies and minds and
thoughts which come and go which pop in
and out of existence and they borrow
existence and they appear to exist for a
while then they lose existence and the
god of them they die or are destroyed
and conclusion being I am that pure
existence I am that infinite that
unlimited existence always experienced
and every other thing in the world that
other thing other than X explained
existence in itself it has no existence
they are all appearances they are what
is called mithya the faults the apparent
and it said the one who is clear about
this this is
the Jeevan Muktha the enlightened while
living this is the goal of Vedanta to
live like this but I know my real nature
and everything in the world is an
appearance in me nothing in the world
can shake me because I am beyond death
and beyond change the real me not the
body not the mind not this little person
so the enlightened person is very clear
about these two this is the ones who are
enlightened they know these two
separately what are the two the real
pure being which I am and appearance
name and far which appears in me and
disappears in me these two are very
clear for the enlightened person now
moving on 17th verse so it is a very
philosophical verse but what is the
practical conclusion of that verse what
what follows 17th verse I mean she
tutored with the Avena she tutored with
d yay me don totem yay no saruba me dumb
totem veena Shamas jasja we know some
obvious jasja knockers chitkul - Moratti
knockers chitkul - Marathi but know that
by which all this is pervaded to be
imperishable no one can bring about the
destruction of this immutable principle
if there are two things one which is
pure being which is the one which truly
exists and the other appearance which
never exists did not exist in the past
will not exist in the future and even
when it seems to exist right now because
of borrowed existence it has no
intrinsic existence it's just borrowed
it from pure being so these are two
things
now if the appearance the world of
appearance names
and forms Maya this samsara - what
category does it belong such our asset
pure being or appearance it belongs to
the category of appearance and what did
the earlier verse say pure being
never goes out of existence and the and
appearance never really comes into
existence in other words all that truly
exists is pure being Brahman Atman and
what seems to exist right now this never
not does not actually exist what what is
existence here is that pure being which
means this world has no existence and
what seems to exist here is because this
is none other than that pure being I'll
repeat that pure being alone exists but
we experience it as this world the
example which I liked very much was in
via in Canada it was last year I think
in Loon Lake the beautiful place in
British Columbia and it was a spiritual
retreat there and if you get up early in
the morning before any wind blows it's
very still and the water is very very
clear it's a vast lake surrounded by
dense forests and hills so you can see
in the early morning light if you look
the water seems absolutely transparent
and if you look into the lake what will
you see not water what appears to you
sky and hills and forests even if birds
fly you can see all of that but in the
lake what is there are there forests
there trees there birds there mountains
there no it's just water and water and
water the trees are water the mountains
are water the sky is water the birds
flying are water everything that you see
there is water in fact when you look
inside and see your own face its water
only there it is water alone which
exists really but what you were
experiencing are things people entities
even actions birds flying around and all
that exactly in the same way but
remember in this is an example don't
extend it too far because example there
is there is really a world outside which
is being reflected in that water
so don't stretch it is there a world
which is being reflected in Brahman no
in the case of Brahman pure awareness in
which it appears pure being and pure
awareness it can project by its own let
us say Maya it it is colored by the
appearance of samsara so it says here
itself when you are experiencing the
world
what follows is number one here itself
is that Brahman pervading all of this I
mean are she to that with that
indestructible that pure being
no it we're in a servo medium Tatem a
very beautiful phrase by which all of
this is pervaded all of this is pervaded
by that but then why don't we all of
what all of this experience what we are
experiencing right now all of it is
pervaded that by that Brahman which you
are but then you might ask why don't we
see it then why don't we experience it
as such in the water in the case of the
lake if you pay attention you can see
the water also you can notice that it is
water but by don't be see Brahman pure
being then why don't we experience it he
uses a word krishna uses the word here
taught now that means literally means
that and if you see the play of words
sarvam idam in sanskrit it done means
this that means that so what this know a
little bit of Sanskrit grammar here this
the word this is always used when it's
something is immediately available for
experience for perception so you can see
it hear it smell it taste it touch it so
if you call it this this thing which I
see or hear or smell or taste or touch
and we generally use taught that for
something which is
remote which is not immediately
available to your senses that place and
this place this place is something here
that place is something there in English
also we use this and that that is remote
and this is approximate in Sanskrit
parotia approach a parochial protection
protection means available to the senses
by using the word that for forward for
that pure being Krishna is indicating
it's not available for your senses just
as the world is available for your
senses you can see it hear it smell it
taste it you can interact with it all
the time you are hearing smelling
tasting names and forms but it's given
reality by that being but that is not an
object for senses it's be it's not
something that you can see it's not
something that you can hear or smell or
taste or touch it's beyond the senses
open you should say address I'm
literally invisible to the senses or
grime you it is not an object for your
motor organs that means you cannot walk
to it or grasp it so that's why the word
Tut has significance here then he uses a
beautiful phrase yena sarvam idam tatam
by which all this is pervaded very
beautiful phrase it makes all the
difference between high philosophy and a
living philosophy between abstraction
beautiful abstraction very clever
philosophy and a Living philosophy
available to all of us yeah in a servo
Adam Tatum see one might say what is
available to me what is available to me
is this world not your abstract
philosophy and he says yes the by that
thing which we spoke about this world of
yours is pervaded through and through
it's available right here llena sarvam
idam tatam by which all is that is that
pervades everything all this is pervaded
by that pure being one might ask how is
it per
it because pervading might mean here is
a room it was dark and we switched on
the lights so the lights have light has
pervaded the room but remember light is
something different in the room is
something different the room can exist
without the light and lights also can
exist without a room so room and light
two different things and one can pervade
the other or another way sometimes we
will light the incense here so you light
the incense here the fragrance pervades
the room so fragrance is one thing and
the room is something else and one thing
pervades the other is Brahma and pure
being like that is there a world and
then Brahman enters it like smoke or
like fragrance or like light it could be
like like it pervades and it's not a
silly idea it's a profound philosophy
Sankhya says that some cases there's a
material universe pervaded by the light
of consciousness
it will there'll be a duality is that
what krishna means no how do you know he
doesn't mean that he's already said it
in the 16th verse only one of them
exists the other appears to exist if
both of them existed see the incense and
the room both exist in our example the
light and the room both exist as a
duality in Sankhya consciousness and
matter both exist independent of each
other they interact but here he says one
exists other one borrows existence from
the other one for from the first one so
it is not like that and what is it like
it's like that loon lake example I gave
you in the lake the trees and the sky
and the rocks and the hills they don't
exist they appear what exists is only
water and water pervade that entire
scenery there in the lake snow of all
shapes all are pervaded by the same
water elements golden ornaments of all
shapes and sizes and types
varieties all are pervaded by the gold
waves in the ocean clay in the pod
classic examples in vedanta clay in the
pot all paul kinds of pottery pottery
barn huh Amsterdam Avenue today it's
pervaded by clay all out pervade but
just how are they pervaded it's not that
there is a part and clay walks in there
hello mr. part I'm going to pervade you
know the part is virtually constituted
of the clay through and through the
waves are constituted of water through
and through icebergs are constituted of
of the dead water through and through no
matter what the shape or the size or the
form ornaments extraordinary variety of
forms all pervaded through and through
by one substance cold in the same way
Brahman that pure existence pervades
everything that we experience through
and through there's a nice two phrases
they use in the Himalayas and among the
monks you can appreciate it I'll in
Hindi they are very effective I'll tell
you in Hindi and translate it into
English this pervading everything
pervaded by God through and through I'm
using the word God as the absolute
Brahman pure being the word the phrase
they use Tassajara super food it's a
it's a very homely phrase purple means
filled up trans AHA just means packed
there's not the slightest space for
anything else left there is in Brahman
there is not the slightest space for any
samsara in the lake where I saw all that
is there any space for mountains and
trees no it's full of water they had
departed and given it can come and trees
can come and stay here than sky can be
here and the mountain can be enough so
it is pervaded in that way pure being
pervades our experienced universe in
that way
now this this phrase by which all is all
this is pervaded yena sarvam idam tatam
tata means be optimum in sanskrit repto
means pervading this comes three times
in the bhagavad-gita and in the context
is beautiful once it comes here the
seventeenth verse of second chapter the
other time it comes in the 22nd verse of
the eighth chapter its 22nd verse is
purusa upper part bhakti obvious to a
new yo your son tetani Buitoni
yena sarvam idam tatam llena sarvam idam
tatam it says that there is the
transcendent being who can be attained
only by devotion by one point devotion
by love in whom all beings exist by
which this entire world is pervaded the
anus of a medium top who are they
talking about they're talking about God
do you see the interesting thing in the
second chapter who is it talking about
he's talking about you you are that pure
being because the whole subject was the
self Atma and he's using this exactly
the same language to talk about God
because when he uses the term bhakti by
one point devotion whom do you have one
I know we have one point to devotion to
ourselves especially here in Manhattan I
mean mine but is one point of devotion
is usually meant for God he's using
exactly the same way - same language to
talk about God and you the real you
you are the transcendent being pure
existence by which the entire universe
is pervaded which constitutes tenth
existence of the entire universe one and
many many I don't know how many months
it will take when we come to the a
chapters 22nd verse we have power
there he's talking about God devotional
and he says there is such a thing
one-pointed surrender and devotion you
will realize that reality that
transcendent reality para Purusha the
transcendent being by which all in which
all beings exist and you can understand
exactly how all beings exist in that
because that is pure being and by which
all is pervaded exactly the same verse
but how do you attain it by love he says
by devotion bhakti again the third time
this comes is at the very end of the
bhagavad-gita the 46th verse of 18th
chapter the last chapter yet
appropriately bhutanam yena sarvam idam
tatam soccer Myrna Tamagotchi sedum
vendetta manova from which has emerged
all activity in the universe of all
beings by which all this is pervaded
same phrase that one worshiping that one
by your work by your action you'll
attain perfection when you recite this I
don't know if people have heard Swami
ranganatham giri immediately reminded of
him this was one of his favorite verses
soccer monoatomic I can see it clearly
sitting there erect sharp soccer
monatomic betcha sid dim vendetta manova
by worshipping the lord by one's actions
activities one attains to perfection
again talking about God there so in
three places very beautiful there is
another one another place in the ninth
chapter fourth verse a similar a similar
phrase is used just one word east maya
tatam idam sarvam by being all this is
pervaded instead of saying by that all
this is pervaded by me all this is
pervaded krishna says
but Stan is out of a boot Ani not sure
much tani and he says much tani
sarva-bhutanam in ninth chapter yes
ninth chapter four verse by the way if
you are impressed how is he cruising all
across the bhagavad-gita I could see
that in some of your faces don't be
impressed I put in hard work I mean I
was studying it today but yes there are
people I have personally known people
who who are so well versed in this and
that it's I am using their work actually
so that's why it seems like magic
somebody else has put in the hard work
maya tatam idam sarvam jagged object
martina so you can understand it
immediately all this is pervaded by me
in my unmanifest invisible phone what is
the unmanifest invisible form pure being
isness much townies are Babu Thani
natural home to show us theta all beings
are in me what's the magic here all
beings are in me yet I am NOT in them
what does it mean imagine somebody
mistakes a rope for a snake can you say
that snake though mistaken that snake is
in actually in the Rope the Rope can say
yes it may be mistaken in me but I am
NOT in that snake that doesn't exist at
all
similarly what does it mean it's only
this only the Rope which exists it's
only pure being it's only God it's only
absolute which exists it's not that the
absolute exists and the world exists and
the absolute exists in the world
no that's what Krishna is saying that is
pure Advaita the next verse after that
the tenth verse that the fifth verse of
ninth chapter it says not your master
naboo Thani pashya may yoga mushroom
these two verses together when we come
to it eventually
many many
later for ten fifth words of nine
chapter they established add weight of
åland and maya what he says is there
that I pervade this entire universe in
my invisible form unmanifest from as
pure being all beings are in me and I am
in them and the next he says in truth
none of them are in mead he flat-out
contradicts himself he says his all
beings are me the next verse he says
they are not in me Bechet me yoga my
firm look at the power of my mind which
means they are appearing in me can the
lake Lake Loon Lake not say I pervade
all these trees and plants and mountains
and skies in the lake by my power water
but in my existence as water all these
plants and lakes and mountains and sky
is in me yet I am NOT in them and in
truth none of them are in me
would it not be perfectly right yes
exactly like that that's the lake here
it means you you the pure being pure
awareness entire world of your
experience appears in you shines in you
disappears in you you pervade it all all
right now when I say these things
remember my sources are of course the
original bhagavad-gita and a variety of
commentaries ancient medieval and modern
once in a while if something occurs to
me I will tell you but I'll flag it so
that you know it's not coming from any
venerable source is just coming from
this guy so what occurred to me today
this is not from any kind of commentary
when I was looking at the three plus one
four occurrences of this phrase ii
chapter 8 chapter 9th chapter 18 chapter
you know what occurred to me notice the
18 chapter clearly is karma yoga
worshiping the lord by your action you
attain to perfection the whole teaching
of Salama Krishna Vivekananda seeing
Shiva in all beings worship them with
service
she began eg was ever exactly it follows
from that the one in the eighth chapter
lobbyists to bhakti on a nearby it is
attainable by one pointed devotion by
love by devotion but Tioga then the
ninth chapter where he clearly puts out
advaita all beings are me yet I am NOT
in them and truly speaking not none of
these are in me the universal actually
not in me they're not at the same level
Brahman and Maya both are implied there
gianni yoga and this one though we have
been explaining it in terms of Advaita
following Shankara actually this is what
is called Sankhya yoga the chapter name
nil chattery Sankhya yoga it did the
very language here is a seung-heon
language Advaita follows from this no
doubt especially in the earlier verse
sixteen twirls
you have to interpret it if you take it
without interpretation you actually get
a kind of Sankhya Sankhya and and yoga
there what are called they are sister
philosophies in Sanskrit Samana Tantra
darshan they are not they are not in
conflict Raja Yoga is the way of
meditation so now you have got the four
occurrences of this one verse from which
follow Raja yoga in order Raja yoga then
bhakti yoga Gianni yoga and karma yoga
so just that just sort of seemed to me
this has been put in these four ways
throughout the book but anyway
and he goes on to say that one practical
implication is Vinh are some of the SCO
NACA streetcar temerity of this pure
being which is unchanging nobody can
destroy it
there's nobody nothing can destroy this
pure being which means he's talking to
Arjuna it does not depend on whether you
fight or you do not fight what will
happen all these bodies these
personalities they will die they will
die they are they belong to that
category which never really came into
existence because they belong to the
category of the false the apparent they
have borrowed existence they are bound
to lose it all those who are worried
about whether you you kill them in war
or you do not kill them in what no death
is certain for all of them none of us
can avoid that death of the body is
certain and your debt is impossible you
cannot die you the real you the spirit
dies not the body will die there's
absolutely nothing to be worried about
there maybe that's what what terrorizes
the world death that's the final
instrument of Maya which keeps us in
terror and he says here this message of
hope be clear about this the body will
not survive no matter what you what you
want to do to it no matter how much
gluten-free and yoga and the self pure
self is never subject to death it really
does not depend on what you do that's
what he wants to tell Arjuna what else
do I want to say about this a couple of
points one is
by this pure being is pervaded this
entire universe by that pure being is
pervaded this entire universe
now when Brahman pervades everything
pure being pervades everything it does
so equally all differences are in Maya
there is no difference in Brahman in the
high and the low in the living and the
non-living in male and female in people
of different races in human beings and
animals alike the same divinity where I
can to put it he says in his inimitable
way he says verily the lowest worm is
brother to the Nazarene Jesus Christ
Avatara Krishna Christ Buddha the
highest product we can think of in in
our civilization in human humanity
unreachable almost divinity in human
form and he says the worm is brother to
that in what he means is it's same
reality everywhere yes manifestation is
different there is difference there's
tremendous difference but all difference
is in manifestation is in Maya in
reality there's only one one reality
this is the tremendous conclusion of
Advaita Vedanta so this is one thing
this the oneness of all existence and
the sameness in down deep the sameness
hence what is the what is the practical
implication the practical implication is
that when we inhabit this world of
difference when we inhabit this world of
difference the implication is respect
the implication is harmony don't fight
don't murder or kill specially in the
name of religion you can see shades of
my world of world Parliament early to
talk here
yeah so how many follows from this the
sameness of the divinity how can you
condemn another person another race
another gender because the same divinity
is there yeah are you going to condemn
God Swami Vivekananda was much was was
he never spared the Hindus for their
faults you know very interesting how he
defended Hinduism staunchly when he was
here against all critics but when he
went back to India he pointed out the
faults of the Hindu society at that time
in no uncertain terms
he said no religion in the world
preaches the glory of a fit of human
nature which means the divinity in such
magnificent wonderful terms as Hinduism
does but no religion in the world treads
on the necks of the on tramples on the
necks of the poor and the weak in there
in such fashion as Hinduism does which
means through caste ISM he pointed out
two things one is the oppression of the
masses another one neglect of the women
this is the two great national sins of
India you pointed out did this does not
follow from Advaita Vedanta it cannot
Vedanta is the most advaitha is the most
democratic of all religions in what
sense the central idea of democracy is
who said that I forget very recently I
heard somebody saying it democracy is
the central idea the central idea of
democracy is that the political power
lies in each of us equally and the
central idea of Vedanta is divinity God
lies in each of us equally that's why he
thought that the United States he loved
America for its ideals of freedom and
human dignity
he felt this country's most suited for
Advaita not so much India though Indians
take it very quickly because they are
used to it culturally but India has has
a very ancient society stratified layer
the layer of hierarchy and tremendous
burden of history is there but here he
found here is a fresh land with where
which values freedom and liberty at of
freedom and dignity what he tried to
give was a spiritual philosophy for the
ideals enshrined in the American
Constitution actually anyway that's
apart from our our talk today there is
one one more thing they wanted to point
out before we go further Oh an
interesting point again a little bit of
Sanskrit grammar here the second line it
says venosum abuse here a Sein occur
streetcar cut to Marat if I translate
the first line said that indestructible
reality by that everything here is
pervaded that and remember why he said
that because it's not accessible to
senses that reality by which this
samsara is pervaded that means beyond
our senses this means which we can
interact with but strangely enough in
the second line he says that and he says
nobody can destroy this unchanging
reality
he uses the word hacia of this
unchanging reality nobody can accomplish
the destruction they are off this is I'm
trying to it's clumsy in English if you
translate that way but what I want to
point out is for Brahman for that
ultimate reality he has used two words
the first sentence he says that reality
in the second sentence he says this
reality pointing out there by it's not
inaccessible it's not beyond our reach
it is in fact continuously accessible
how is it accessible didn't you just say
we can't see it hear it smell it taste
it touch it we can't walk to it we can't
hold it by our hands
it's not accessible to any of our
instruments it's accessible in this way
let us say all of this all of you here
are accessible what is the proof that I
experience you I will say I see you what
is the proof that you are here today I
will say I saw them so the proof for
your existence here is my seeing you
seeing proof for existence hold onto
this seeing is the proof for existence
now what is the proof for the existence
of my eyes will you say seeing no I
can't see my eyes let me make it even
more interesting what is the proof that
there was no elephant in the room if
there was an elephant I would have seen
it I do I didn't see it therefore there
is no elephant the proof for the
non-existence of the elephant is I did
not see it the proof for your existence
here today is I saw it so the proof of
existence is seeing proof of
non-existence not seeing now I cannot
see my eyes therefore my eyes do not
exist what's wrong with it
this rule applies only to objects to
objects objects are revealed by your
awareness the presence of objects is
revealed by your awareness the absence
of objects is revealed by your awareness
both the presence and absence of objects
reveal your awareness they point to the
fact that you are consciousness itself
it's a very crucial point how do you see
God in every experience this is the
answer to that in every experience God
is being continuously revealed to us let
me use two words revealed and manifested
the light reveals this book to you here
and the book manifests the existence of
light
you the consciousness you the existence
you reveal this world you give this
world its existence and this world of
appearances manifests your being that
you are pure being pure awareness some
of your getting it
isn't it beautiful yes right what did I
say both the presence of objects and the
absence of objects are revealed by your
consciousness and both the presence and
absence of objects reveal your
consciousness how do you say that you
are sleeping when you are able to say
when you wake up how did you say that
you're sleeping because something
revealed sleeping to you not at that
moment you cannot say because mind is
not working senses are not working mind
and senses have gone to sleep hence you
cannot think I am sleeping you cannot
say I am sleeping if you could say that
you wouldn't be sleeping in that funny
thing mothers the test the children has
the goodbye gone to sleep if he has gone
to sleep
his right leg will move in the right leg
moves little bit and mother is
pretending the kids he had a hard time
to put them to make them sleep they
become hyperactive just before bedtime
so you cannot express that I am sleeping
and here is an experience it's an
experience of absence it's not the
absence of experience deep sleep is not
the absence of experience
by these words that and this that pure
being
points out it's not something that you
can experience with your senses this
pure being points out that it is
continuously available to you as your
very self which gives existence and
consciousness in in it reveals the world
and gives existence to the world in
sanskrit the words are very nice satis
40 citta means exists at means existence
citta means that borrowed existence chit
means consciousness fruity means the
shining forth sporran in Sanskrit
shining forth expression the world is it
shines forth yes
what someone else when you say someone
else there is no someone else there is
only one being the moment you say the
real I look at the language you used the
real eye is a limitless I think about it
you can if you get what what we're
talking about you can actually check in
your own experience is awareness limited
where is the end of awareness is it
limited in time does it come to an end
time flows in awareness is it limited in
space I've given the example one monk in
Uttarakhand said hey how do you say
Swami stop how do you say that I am
all-pervading I'm here I'm not even
there how can I be all-pervading
question I'm here I'm not even there how
can I be all-pervading answer was
immediate answer was ahh
but here and there are they both not in
your awareness in your dream you are
standing here looking at something there
here and there in fact the entire
universe in your dream was it not in
your mind there is no limit to awareness
no limit to pure being all limits are in
pure being if you say that is it so what
how does it relate to my question
relates in this way if it live all
limits are in pure being then where is
the limit between you and another person
bodies are limited they're different
minds are limited consciousness flowing
through this mind is the person who is
asking the question but that
consciousness in itself is the same for
everybody or rather in that what did we
say in that awareness all beings exist
or they do not even exist
that awareness alone exists there is no
anybody else what you are saying at a
practical level yes there is a
difference the way you are perceiving
this and the way she is perceiving he is
pursuing slightly different because you
are perceiving it through through this
medium of your senses
and to the filter of your mind same for
each of us but that's at a practical
level yes each of us is a difference we
put a little layer up on the world that
we perceive we do not we really do not
have any access to the world outside
everything that we perceive is through
the medium of our minds and our minds
our eyes play around and disappear in
awareness awareness and mind are not the
same so my answer to you is no you are
the answer to your question lies in your
very very question does someone else
give a different existence to it no
there is no someone else in your dream
for example you see so many people in so
many places and somebody tells you all
of this is given in existence by you the
Dreaming mind and if you ask all those
people are they giving some existence to
all these things also all those people
are also given existence by your
Dreaming mind in the dream here not by
your mind you are not dreaming all this
it is rather in pure being pure
consciousness all things appear yeah yes
yeah I'm repeat that awareness imparts
existence yes right how do you explain
that but remember with the way you are
using awareness and what is meant here
is slightly different the way you are
using awareness is awareness channel
through our minds what you're saying is
this awareness in Mead a person has made
certain things it's object certain
things the awareness is seeing certain
things it's hearing something things
it's remembering this is my area of
knowledge and beyond this is a vast area
of darkness where I don't know and so is
it it is true for all of us
but this is awareness which is what is
called baraha Rica it is channeled
through a body and a mind certainly for
us there are things we know things we do
not know but all of this body's mind
senses and vishaya objects they all
appear in the ground of reality again
very easy to understand if you take your
dream world in your dream world you have
a world in that you are also there and
there that person who is there in the
dream that person knows certain things
and also has the feeling there are many
things in this world which I do not know
but they exist even if I do not know but
is it true what is true is that all of
that exists only or appears only in the
dreamers mind from the point of view of
the person inside the dream there are
things which are known and things are
known both known and unknown are
appearances in consciousness we have to
think like that
yes
it's tremendous really what he's saying
right here itself hey Dante is already
over all right now he goes on in
contrast to this what about the bodies
our minds these things of the world they
all have a beginning and an end
so he says 18 twerks krishna says unto
and he made and he made a neat just
choked ashurina huh neat just so sorry
Rena no she no premier yes
annachi you know from me yes smart you
just the smart these bodies of the
eternal imperishable immeasurable
embodied self are said to have an end
wear for fight or descendent of Bharata
now what about this life this first of
all this particular body this particular
manifestation in awareness it has a
beginning it has grown it has it will
age it will pass away do not worry about
it as long as it exists take care of it
use it act in this world very
interesting what follows from all this -
ah Sophie does not you - well again and
again and again Krishna he has a motive
in all of this to engage Arjuna in the
Mahabharata war but what follows from
what seems to be a very abstract
philosophy is a philosophy of action it
enables you to act properly in this
world without attachment without
ambition greed without fear and terror
it enables you to act with serenity in
this world to do the best you can
through that particular body and mind
the smart you just were fight the battle
of life o Bharata out o descendant of
the Parata under one time a day these
bodies are with beginnings and ends with
which means with beginning and end and
they are appearances of what Mattia of
the eternal reality which you are and
that eternal reality seems to possess a
body now it's called sure eerie the
embodied embody does not mean there is a
body and then you are filled into the
body a poured into the body somehow no
it means just that I accept this body as
as mine in Hindi this is secret imatra
you just said this is mine
when one begins to see this if you put
some attention to it you will begin to
see it is nothing more than an
identification that it is mine that's
all that I say it's really there is no
connection between you and the body
imagine where we have gone from from I
am the body and nothing else - now we
are saying there's nothing to be there's
no connection between you and the body
Mitscher Irina the embodied embodied
means the one who claims that this body
is mine sure eerie I remember Swami Rama
Krishna and the Hashima Raj he was in
Chennai at that time and sister daivam
at an American lady an American nun she
had gone to India - she stayed for some
time met many of the direct disciples of
Sri Ramakrishna including Shahi Mardan
Swami Rama Krishna energy one day she
writes in a reminiscence his days in an
Indian monastery she writes in a
reminiscences that the Swami was talking
about the difficulties he had faced in
setting up that and hardships tremendous
hardships he had faced for example I
remember many such stories poverty
extreme poverty and one day there is
nothing to offer to the - sri
ramakrishna there is a ritualistic
offering every day
Bogg is offered so nobody had bought
anything no offerings from devotees
fruits or sweets something that can be
offered and Swami Rama Krishna and the
who had won that's why his name was
Ramakrishna and the one whose bliss is
in
krishna at one point devotion to ram
krishna he goes to Sri Ramakrishna in
inner half and he says all right if
nothing comes today I shall go to the
beach in Madras under and I will make
little like coconut balls I will make
little balls of sand and I'll come and
offer that to you today as as the
offered food and I will eat that and
live today as he said this somebody
little by later somebody turned up at
the monastery
a devotee with a lot of delicious foods
and everything so Salama krishna he can
be threatened yes immediately all sorts
of nice food came up and turned up
anyway so he told many stories and how
he had struggled he was a powerful
figure
but apparently and his talks well
they're not very you know very
entertaining let's put it this way
it was a very serious man Ramakrishna ng
so sometimes his talks were very poorly
attended but whatever if even one person
turned up he would go and give the talk
he would go to different parts of
Chennai and give the talk he'd go in a
rickshaw sometimes and give the talk
there he wouldn't touch money he would
ask people gave money so he would ask
them them to tie it on his dhoti
donations for the ministry and it so
happened one day interracial rain and
that place is flooded he invades through
knee-deep water dirty water ended in the
sewers there to go to the place we just
to give a talk and he goes there because
just to give a talk that nobody has
turned up he sits there gives the talk
and comes back so he said I'm not doing
it for a person I'm offering it to the
Lord the Lord is always present it is
seriously meant it and so on so many
many experiences he tells and sister
Dave Mata writes that I was indignant
why should a person like Swami Rama
Krishna and the saintly person why did
he have to suffer so much I felt so bad
so I said to him why Swami why did you
have to serve
so much and then she writes he looked
startled and surprised and he said what
are you saying my real life is infinite
let the Lord play with this little life
as he will nietzsche of the eternal this
little life born yesterday - fated to
die tomorrow what is it - you give it to
the Lord and let the Lord play with it
as even so that is what he says yes your
Tasha arena and there and thus act
don't sit idly act do what is in front
of you
annachi no cannot be destroyed from me
alright let me explain this important
point a premiere means not an object to
the pramanas that means the instruments
of knowledge how do we know something by
seeing hearing smelling tasting touching
by inferring through science by you know
through logic inference by testimony
from others we know in a various ways in
in various sources of knowledge are
there for us however all you know
whatever you know you can know through
Google today so all of these are called
pramana which gives you knowledge and
this ultimate reality uh premiere it's
not an object for any of these pramanas
you can read about it in a book even
Google can tell you about it you can
tell you lots about Vedanta but it
really will not give you enlightenment
you cannot grasp it directly through any
of this just the way you can see it with
your eyes you can touch it with your
hand you can see I know it in that way
you cannot know Brahman so it is called
a premiere not an object to these
sources of knowledge sources of
knowledge protection that means direct
perception then anumana
inference and then shooty that means
that that is scripture testimony
instructions from trustworthy sources
shabda pramanas this and there are
secondary pramanas also I mean they're
technically there's something called
supposition like art uppity there is a
new pallab the absence itself is a
pramana we will not go into a lot of
technicalities the whole system the
whole thing is called epistemology the
science of knowledge it's a branch of
laws a very big branch of philosophy but
the point here is all these sources
epistemic sources pramanas do not
operate on brahman so this leads to a
problem the problem is all this you are
saying what is the proof again the same
thing proof that this book exists I see
it and touch it all of us see it so it
exists what is the proof that dispute
being pure consciousness exists what is
the proof I was talking to a philosopher
recently NYU and he said what is the
proof but you're saying that it exists
so such a thing a premiere you know what
is to prove the answer is there in that
example of the eye is seeing what is the
proof you know what a nut waiting will
say he'll say all the sources of proof
the methods methods of knowledge
pramanas they all operate because of it
that consciousness is the one which
powers which lights up all the pramanas
how do you see do the eyes see no it is
consciousness which sees through the
mind and the eyes do the ears here no it
is consciousness which hears being
channelled through the mind and the ears
do does the intellect do science no it
is consciousness channel through the
intellect which which does science it is
consciousness in consciousness and
through consciousness everything is
happening so this is the answer that
Advaita Vedanta gives o it is not an
object to pramanas but all
all pramanas the sanskrit phrases
brahmana serve a pramana premier of ever
harder all activities epistemic
activities are grounded in consciousness
you might say so this is what this leads
to the hard problem of consciousness one
of my favorite subjects yeah it's a
camera there's a camera there the camera
it's recording is it seeing in a way you
can see it's seeing it can record and if
it's connected to computers and devices
it can even react to things happening
but does it have a first-person
experience of seeing inside is there
something which is seeing can the
first-person XP like you are seeing
colors you're hearing sound is that
thing going on in the camera it's
recording light and sound no not even
the most ambitious Sony executive will
claim our cameras are conscious no so
what is that behind all epistemic axis
is consciousness it is not an object to
sources of knowledge but it is that
which powers all sources of knowledge
therefore I'll leave you with this
thought in all knowledge it is available
just as eyes are available in all seeing
though they are not something you see
mind is there in all thinking
similarly consciousness is there in all
experience our attention is it flows
through the objects of experience but if
you know this knowledge is there with
you you can know that consciousness
within quartz No you can know it by
being it Brahma Veda Brahm haver Parvati
the knower of Brahman is none other than
Raman it yes so two questions
this lady first and then I'll go to you
let's call it pure being awareness pure
being awareness I will modify it that's
right I'll modify it in this way she
asked is the continuity in our
experience due to pure being sick let's
call it being awareness such chit
existence consciousness the continuities
and the perceived discontinuities are
all due to that pure being there are
perceived discontinuities deep sleep
anesthesia discontinuities amnesia
memory failure very boring Vedanta class
the class went away in a twinkling of an
eye what happened mind was elsewhere but
that is also revealed by the same
continuous awareness yes question yes
that will come into thirteen chapter
very powerful statement shade to the gum
sharp Imam with deserve Akshay Trisha
Bharata
I am the consciousness in all bodies and
mind literally I am the knower of the
field in all fields this relates
directly to your question the gentleman
here who asked the question other people
because we seal I am the knower of this
field this body is a field in this I am
there as the nor Krishna says how many
nodes are there is it there is only one
nor apparently there are many nodes with
respect to bodies and minds many many
knowers with respect to consciousness
behind the body mind one consciousness
that is what is called God in Vedanta
I am the consciousness I am the knower
of the field in all feel God is
therefore available to us in every
experience inside yourself as yourself
but as your real self capitalist there
was another question that yes that's the
last question
yeah true we don't know in fact the only
thing that you know for sure is that you
see you don't even know that we see how
do you know how do you know you because
you don't have access to our
first-person experiences we could all be
zombies for all you know yes Halloween
just passed yes yes the camera yes yes
correct
the difference between living and
nonliving so this is a issue which is
easily resolved
how does wait on to distinguish between
living beings and non living beings from
Vedantic perspective there is only one
existence consciousness and all things
are names and forms but among these
names and forms there are living names
and forms like us we call them living
beings and there are nonliving names and
forms like tables chairs and the camera
how do you distinguish between them
Vedanta says the word is right there
living in Sanskrit prana prana means
it's a part of what is called the subtle
body right now we have two bodies one is
a physical body and one is a subtle body
see what proof again we don't always go
to your experience you have a dual
experience you experience a physical
body which is public others can see it
your doctor can examine it but you have
an inner experience thoughts feelings
emotions right you seem doubtful
thoughts feelings emotions ideas
memories questions all of those are
there your doctor cannot see it your
doctor can only go up to the brain in
our experience you have got that inner
experience is where is happening in what
is called the subtle body
sukshma sharir which constitutes
constitutes of which is constituted of
the pranamaya kosha monomeric ocean
began a micro shot 3 there's a causal
body beyond that but will not bother
with that so these three are called this
subtle body now the distinction between
living beings and non living beings is
living beings have the subtle body which
has prana which is life mind and
intellect and emotions ideas and
memories the whole person is there that
is called the Jiva tapa and beyond that
is of course causal body and then
consciousness so existence consciousness
is there in that camera also but what
happens is because there is no subtle
body there the only the existence aspect
is manifest as a theme but there is no
person in there because there is no
subtle body in there that's how we
distinguish you'll see why is there not
a subtle body there we can't see if
there was a subtle body it would be a
person this is an important question
because in these days when a eye is
being seriously discussed so I have had
actually people working with AI in some
of the most advanced labs in this
country in a couple of questions a quite
a couple of times I've been asked this
question can this AI they are talking
about a particular project which is
still yeah can it become conscious in
the sense you are talking about so they
have many theories about that from a
vedantic perspective if you can design a
subtle body if you can generate a subtle
body it'll become conscious because
existence consciousness is always there
existence is manifest this is this is
but there is no inner awareness there
there's an inner awareness here because
consciousness is also borrowed see it
happens this way physical bar body
borrows sup being subtle body borrows
being and awareness existence
consciousness this is called Chi dabas
reflected consciousness again your
experience you not only have thoughts
but those hearts shine in consciousness
if you note here onyx inner experience
that consciousness which you are feeling
now that is not pure consciousness
that's the consciousness associated with
a thought shining in a thought
that's called reflected or in sanskrit
pilita Jadhav has a shadow of
consciousness or reflection of
consciousness it's like the sun's light
being reflected from the moon the moon
appears luminous for all practical
purposes shines gives light and all of
that but it's not luminous its borrowing
light from the Sun the mind in itself it
borrows existence and consciousness from
the Atman the body borrows only
existence it cannot because it does not
have the capacity to borrow
consciousness so this is the distinction
again if you say what how what guy but
gives you the right to make this
distinction I say look at your
experience science cannot explain this I
just leave you with and I can't resist
this obviously I've heard of the hard
problem of consciousness I've been
repeating it again and again science has
a problem neuroscience that you go up to
the brain but after that how it has a
first-person experience you can't talk
about it they have a huge debate going
on and New York NY you all of this is at
the nerve center of that debate I
mentioned that last week week before
last there was actually a workshop a
colloquium where some of the top
philosophers were present and Advaita
Vedanta perspective on the heart
consciousness of problem that was hard
hard problem of consciousness was
discussed so it's come to that level now
but on the other hand philosopher
Galanter Strawson from UT Austin
University of Texas Austin he says
forget the hard problem of consciousness
there is no hard problem of
consciousness there is the hard problem
of matter what he says is is very
avoiding he's not saying it in a
reductionist materialist way he's just
saying the opposite he says
consciousness we know what it is you're
all conscious we know we are conscious
matter appears to us in consciousness
and we investigate it with science
common sense science whatever and as we
investigated with science it disappears
before our eyes the more we have
investigated matter it seems to be only
structure nama Rupa where is the
substance it keeps disappearing what is
matter how matter we makes distinction
science tells us a lot about what how
matter behaves it is continuously
failing to tell us what matter is what
is the thing there the moment to
investigate the thing it breaks up into
smaller and smaller and smaller
particles atoms to subatomic particles
to nucleus two protons and neutrons to
quarks to super strings goes further
than the unimaginably receding further
and further back what are you getting
Jim Holt said in his book why does the
world exist we are getting only name we
are getting only structure structure in
my eyes name and form more science
investigates matter all you keep getting
his name and form substance disappears
the most clearly you investigated the
more it fades away so he says Garin
Strawson says he calls it the hard
problem of matter you you forget
consciousness consciousness
everybody knows consciousness because we
are conscious and he says we don't know
what matter is the more science
advantage is just shown us we have
absolutely no idea what matter is if you
put the hard problem of consciousness
and he brought the hard problem of
matter together you get up greater wait
until you get tucked wama see on that we
will end Shanti Shanti Shanti hurry he
that sat sri ramakrishna aparna must